Okay, בוקר טוב, Boker Tov, we’ll talk about that in a minute.
Okay, we pick up today is ק''א, Kuf Aleph, 101. We have
covered 100 דפים, Dappim,
actually at the end of today we’ll have covered 100 דפים Dappim
in כתובות. Kesuvos. We pick up with the Mishnah at the bottom
of ק' עמוד ב'. Kuf Amud Beis. הממאנת, Hamema'enes, a woman who
refuses, meaning she was married off by her brother and mother, her
brothers and mother,
when she was underage. This was done to protect her interests when
there was no father, which speaks to the fact that marrying off
a girl as a minor was actually done for socio-economic reasons because
the Rabbis had to create an institution when there was no father
to allow it to be done. Again, I’ll remind you that we’re
talking about קידושי קטנה, Kiddushei Ketanah,
when it’s clear from the גמרא Gemara that the נישואין Nissuin would
not happen until after at least her בת מצווה. Bas Mitzvah. So
anyway, when that took place it was not biblically binding and she
had the right to refuse anytime prior to her becoming a בת
מצווה. Bas Mitzvah. So she goes ahead and she does refuse and
then retroactively we say there was never any קידושין. Kiddushin. Okay, or
השנייה, Hashniya, a woman who is a rabbinic, meaning second degree, not
first, not first degree, not primary but secondary
restriction because of a relative, but only a rabbinically defined relative, not
a biblically defined relative. Case of somebody that's a certain degree removed.
I'm not going to remind us all מסכת יבמות. Masechet Yevamos. Okay,
but rabbinically forbidden because of a form of extended form of incest.
And האיילונית, Ha'ailonis, a woman who is not just infertile but actually
has biologically male characteristics, some type of non-developed female characteristics or actually
maybe some even male characteristics and there's something that was seen that
like fundamentally
you know, again, not just that she's infertile but that it was
a woman who never could have had kids, I don't know, it's
a category
where it's like there's a presumption that if the man had known
that this was the case, he never would have married her. It's
a type of a קידושי טעות. Kiddushei Taus.
Meaning if he knew she was an איילונית, Ailonis,
he wouldn't have married her. Yeah, but it's different. That's correct.
What's the
word?
איילונית. Ailonis. איילונית, Ailonis, which is אייל Ayil is like the ram,
you know, so it's somehow, which is male, so it's somehow some
woman that has male characteristics, doesn't fully develop,
and is also infertile, and that's the type of woman that חז''ל
Chazal understood the man had he known would not have married her.
I don't know how they case it under...
well, that's what I'm about to say. Okay. אין להן כתובה. Ein
Lahen Kesuvah. So in this case, when they leave the husband they
don't get a כתובה. Kesuvah. Why? Well, the ממאנת Mema'enes because retroactively
she was never married when she refuses. The איילונית Ailonis because it
was a מקח טעות, Mekach Taus, so it was never a marriage.
And the שנייה Shniya because it's a violation, we don't want them
to be married, so we're not going to enforce it and we're
not going to you know, support it through a כתובה. Kesuvah. If
there's no כתובה Kesuvah then hopefully people will refuse, certainly the women
will refuse. What?
It's also all the other marriages we don't like.
Well, we'll take a look. ולא פירות ולא מזונות, V'lo Peiros, V'lo
Mezonos, and
therefore not פירות. Peiros. Now פירות Peiros seems to be a benefit
that the man gets, that he eats the fruit from the woman's
estate, but because the emphasis of this is that the woman is
the one who is being penalized,
at least in the case of the שנייה. Shniya. In the other
cases, I should say, by the ממאנת Mema'enes and the איילונית, Ailonis,
since there was never a marriage, so the man doesn't get the
benefits either, so ולא פירות V'lo Peiros could mean literally he doesn't
get the פירות Peiros because there was never a marriage so therefore
he didn't get the benefits of the כתובה. Kesuvah. But in the
case of the שנייה, Shniya, there's an assumption that we want to
penalize her to prevent her from agreeing to the marriage. I'll elaborate
on that in a minute. So רש''י Rashi here says that the
word פירות Peiros does not mean the man's getting of the fruit
from her property, but what she gets in exchange, which is the
right to be redeemed if she's taken captive. ולא מזונות, V'lo Mezonos,
she does not get ongoing support in terms of food. ולא בלאות,
V'lo Bla'os, and not worn out
property, which either means that when she leaves because you know, whatever,
she gets a divorce in the case of the שנייה Shniya or
she refuses or whatever, she doesn't take her worn out clothing with
her, any property she brought in even if it's sort of worn
out, she has to leave behind. All the property she brings in
she leaves behind. Okay, or there's another way to read it because
it says property that has actually been consumed that she brought in,
she does not get reimbursed for. So basically she's like being stripped
of everything. It's like worse than when you go sort of like
free your slave here. Here she leaves you know,
she leaves completely with nothing.
What?
Is מזונות Mezonos the ones when she's married?
So, and or when she's married, but it also would mean that
if she borrowed money in order to pay for her food bill
and now she's getting divorced or she's leaving because she's ממאנת, Mema'enes,
she cannot ask for reimbursement.
So it's retroactive, in other words because as long as she's not
ממאנת Mema'enes they're just married.
Right. Right. So it would mean that there was an outstanding bill
to be paid that she had forwarded the money for. She cannot
get reimbursed. That is correct. אם תחילה נשאה לשם אילונית im techila
nisa'ah l'shem ilunnis and here it's explicit, if he knew she was
an אילונית ilunnis then it was not a מקח טעות mekach taut
and יש לה כתובה yesh la kesuba she has a כתובה. kesuba.
So okay. So that's a case where again either just practically they
were never married, שניה shniya is the most interesting of that, that
specifically they were married, it was binding, but the rabbis stripped her
of the כתובה kesuba and of her rights. And what's going to
particularly be shocking is the end of the mishna: אלמנה לכהן גדול
גרושה וחלוצה לכהן הדיוט ממזרת ונתינה לישראל. almanah l'kohen gadol grushah v'chalutzah
l'kohen hedyot mamzeret u'nesinah l'yisrael. If it's a biblically forbidden marriage, but
it's only a לאו, lav, a negative prohibition, so it's not a
כרת. kares. כרת kares would not be binding at all. With a
negative prohibition, it's binding even though it's prohibited. So what's a case
of a simple negative prohibition? A כהן גדול kohen gadol marrying a
widow, a normal כהן kohen marrying a divorcée or a woman who's
done חליצה chalitzah to it, or a ממזרת mamzeret or נתינה. nesinah.
I'm not going to discuss what נתינה nesinah is, but a ממזרת
mamzeret marrying a ישראל yisrael or a ישראל yisrael woman marrying a
ממזר. mamzer. In all those cases, it's a biblical prohibition but it's
binding. יש להן כתובה. yesh lahen kesuba. She's still entitled to the
כתובה, kesuba, which is bizarre, right? Why should she get a כתובה?
kesuba? I mean, why should we ever want to endorse, you know,
this marriage? So basically, the rabbis understand the following, which is, I
mean you could have just said any כתובה kesuba is an implicit
endorsing of the marriage and we should just never allow it period.
But the way at least sort of רש"י Rashi and רש"י Rashi
explains it is that we actually want to sort of see this
as a vehicle, as a tool that will prevent these marriage this
marriage from taking place. So we feel the following, this is the
way רש"י Rashi explains. In the case where it's a שניה, shniya,
where it's only a rabbinic issue, she feels like look,
you know, it's not going to impact my status, like I'm not
going to be אסור asur to a כהן kohen as a result
of this type of an act, and it's not going to impact
my kids' status, they're not, you know, so I'm not really losing
too much out of it, even though it's some rabbinic problem, and
therefore she's more interested in getting married and she's going to go
ahead and try to persuade him—again, interesting assumption that like she's the
one that's going to be persuading him—you know, and she's going to
seduce him into getting married even though it's this rabbinic prohibition. So
somehow we have to penalize her to prevent her from doing that.
Okay, but if it is a biblical prohibition, you know, then the
way רש"י Rashi says it here—let me see if I can read
you the רש"י. Rashi.
If you take a look at the second wide line of רש"י,
Rashi, where he says אלמנה לכהן גדול almanah l'kohen gadol middle line
יש לה כתובה yesh la kesuba מפני שהיא פסולה וולדה פסול על
ידי נישואין. mipnei she-hi psulah v'valadah pasul al yedei nisuin.
So therefore, if they have an—I guess if you marry a כהן,
kohen, right, it makes you like a חללה, chalalah, so it can
affect her status. So since it could affect her status for a
כהן kohen when it's a biblical prohibition, לפיכך אינה מגילתו. lefichach einah
megilato.
So we're not afraid that she's going to be trying to get
the marriage to take place because this type of a thing could
affect her status. אלא, ela, so if somebody is trying to get
the marriage taking place, it's probably
him. הוא מגילה ומשדלה לינשא hu megila u'mshadlah l'hinasei because it's not
going to affect my status, it's only going to affect her status.
So therefore, they wanted to fine him, and the way they fine
him—they didn't really fine him, but at least he continues to incur
the financial responsibilities of the כתובה. kesuba. Okay, which is again, with
all that being said, A: not all these cases are כהן kohen
related cases. It stays in the עבודה. avodah. And well, maybe. Anyway,
not all these cases are כהן kohen related cases, but more troubling
is just having the presence of the rabbinically instituted כתובה kesuba for
a marriage is an implicit condoning and recognizing of the marriage. So,
you know, it's very bizarre that they would ever say יש לה
כתובה, yesh la kesuba, even if we understand that there's some benefit
that, oh well, if there's going to be some financial cost—look, the
financial cost to him is not going to be any more than
the financial cost of any marriage. So there's absolutely nothing in this
scenario, you know, that creates an incentive for him not to get
married, that actually, you know, penalizes him, and it comes with it
an implicit condoning of the whole relationship. So it is actually quite
bizarre, you know, this ruling. Now, the one really important question though
is, which is not in this mishna, is does he have an
obligation to pay מזונות mezonot while they're still married? Right, it's one
thing to say when they get divorced, you know, she can still
collect all the outstanding debts and so on. Okay, but it could
be very well be based on other גמרות gemarot that he does
not pay for have an obligation to pay for the מזונות mezonot
while they're married because that would really be helping sustain the relationship,
right, creating those ongoing obligations during during the marriage itself. And if
there aren't those ongoing obligations and she's actually not getting food put
on the table for her, then hopefully—I mean, of course what can
she do about it? She can't divorce him, he can only divorce
her. But anyway, but that does again raises that question that maybe
at least we would say that the ongoing things that are sustaining
the marriage, the financial
structures, maybe that wouldn't be in the place. But the simple sense
of the mishna anyway and the basic ruling still we must admit
is quite bizarre that it does not seem we do anything to
show any sort of condemnation of this biblically forbidden marriage. Okay, so
now let's take a look at the גמרא.
gemara. It’s so bizarre. I mean, it’s separating punishment from approval.
You know, as you said, if there's already a way for, if
there's already something built in that would prevent them from getting married,
dissuade them from getting married, so what’s the point of adding on
something? In other words, it is just a device to affect the
outcome rather than to punish. Once they’re married already, yes,
you know, it’s like if someone lives outside the system and we
have to put them in prison, it doesn’t mean that he abandons
his rights forever after that. So
it’s actually, I don’t know, it doesn’t seem so bizarre.
Yeah, but if you contrast the case of the שניה shniah
and it’s not just he did some other things wrong. What he
did wrong is the very, the very institution of the marriage is,
is prohibited. And we are sort of saying, okay, it’s forbidden but
it’s binding. But how much are we going to give it all
of these sort of structures that normally come with the marriage which
would seem to sort of reinforce it rather than, you know, undermine
it? No, that doesn’t bother you?
No, I think
it’s like, it’s like the difference between, it’s like almost a human
right. You know, just because you have been through things doesn’t mean
you abandon your right to be supported, kosher food.
Well,
I guess especially if you look at it from the wife’s perspective,
right?
But, yeah, once you say it’s binding,
yeah.
All right, but then it gets back to raise the question why
it doesn’t work in the case of the שניות. shnios. All right,
let’s take a look at the גמרא.
Gemara. It could be because it gives, it shows that the rabbis
knew that a lot of the things in the תורה Torah weren’t
going to be kept and we have to accept them anyway. And
this to me reminds me of gay marriage.
That’s a good, yeah, no, it’s a good point. But again, what
I would say is is that fine, but then if you think
that you can deprive the כתובה kesuvah in the case of the
שניה shniah and that there's some effect that's being done in terms
of because of the your disapproval of the second degree עריות, arayos,
right? That's the first הלכה halachah in the משנה. Mishnah. So again,
it’s just ironic that there’s no כתובה kesuvah in a marriage that's
rabbinically forbidden but there is a כתובה kesuvah in a marriage that’s
biblically forbidden. All right, let’s take a look at the גמרא. Gemara.
But I mean, I hear the point. If it was, if it
was consistent I’d get it. Okay, רב, Rav, okay, רב תני קטנה
יוצאה בגט ואין לה כתובה. Rav tani katana yotzei beget v'ein lah
kesuvah. רב Rav had in the משנה Mishnah his, his was not
just that the ממאנת mema'enes doesn’t have a כתובה, kesuvah, but even
if this קטנה ketanah who only is rabbinically married because again it
was done by her, not her father but the mother and the
brothers, if she did not refuse her husband but her husband refused
her, then her husband gave her a גט get as a קטנה,
ketanah, that could also happen. So he in the משנה Mishnah had
that even she doesn’t have a כתובה, kesuvah, אין לה כתובה. ein
lah kesuvah. וכל שכן ממאנת, v'chol shekein mema'enes, certainly if she refuses
and then retroactively there was no marriage. Okay, because here it seems
like there was a marriage at least rabbinic and a divorce, and
even so she doesn’t get a כתובה. kesuvah. Because maybe he figures
that as long as she’s a קטנה ketanah we don’t even really
treat it as serious at all. So it’s not only because she
refuses. Even if he divorced her as long as it all took
place, the marriage and the divorce, while she was a קטנה, ketanah,
while she was a minor, and it wasn’t with the father and
it was, it was really nothing, it was really just play acting
and therefore there’s no כתובה. kesuvah. Okay, שמואל תני ממאנת אין לה
כתובה. Shmuel tani mema'enes ein lah kesuvah. But שמואל Shmuel says no,
the one who refuses doesn’t have a כתובה kesuvah because she retroactively
undermined it.
אבל
יוצאה בגט יש לה כתובה. aval yotzei beget yeish lah kesuvah. If
he divorced her as a קטנה, ketanah, then at least there was
a rabbinic marriage and a rabbinic divorce and therefore she’s entitled to
the
כתובה. kesuvah. דאמר שמואל, d'amar Shmuel, שמואל Shmuel goes according to his
reasoning, דאמר שמואל ממאנת אין לה כתובה. d'amar Shmuel mema'enes ein lah
kesuvah. A somebody, a woman, a girl who refuses doesn’t get her
כתובה. kesuvah. יוצאה
בגט יש לה כתובה.
yotzei
beget yeish lah kesuvah.
If she gets a גט get while she’s a קטנה ketanah she
gets a כתובה. kesuvah. Again, even though it’s only rabbinic, done by
the, by the mother.
ממאנת לא פסלה מן האחים. mema'enes lo paslah min ha-achim. If she
refuses her husband then she is not, she
does not basically make him, לא פסלה, lo paslah,
right. She has not, she has not become
invalid to his brothers. It’s not like she is now this man’s
divorcee and now can’t marry the brothers. No, retroactively there was no
marriage. So therefore she can marry the brothers. ולא פסלה מן הכהונה.
v'lo paslah min ha-kehunah. She’s not a divorcee so she’s not invalid
to marry a כהן, kohen, even though she’s had sex possibly, although
again the נשואין nisuin probably waited until she was בת מצוה. bas
mitzvah. יוצאה בגט, yotzei beget, if he gave her a גט get
as a קטנה, ketanah, פסלה מן האחים, paslah min ha-achim, then she’s
a divorcee at least rabbinically and can't marry the brothers. ופסלה מן
הכהונה, u-paslah min ha-kehunah, can’t marry a כהן. kohen. So again שמואל
Shmuel says if there’s a גט, get, then at least rabbinically it’s
like a marriage and a גט. get. It’s not that there was
nothing. Okay, ממאנת אינה צריכה להמתין שלשה חדשים. mema'enes einah tzerichah l'hamtin
shloshah chodashim. If she refuses her husband and she wants to remarry,
she does not have to wait three months. Now this is quite
fascinating, right, because the waiting of three months was not just a
formalistic rabbinic requirement, but it was a real question about whose child
would it be if she got pregnant right afterwards. So you want
to have that spacing. Now, you could still say a קטנה ktanah
couldn't get, well, some קטנות, ktanos, it may be based on that,
it may be based on the reality that these cases were again
as we've seen before, would normally be קידושין kiddushin without נישואין, nissuin,
okay.
Anyways, so, but it is quite fascinating. Okay, so,
one minute, okay. But right, Michael might be right also, it might
have to do with the fact that we assume that a קטנה
ktanah isn't going to get pregnant. יוצא בגיט, yotzei be-get, if she
gets a גט, get, צריכה להמתין, tzericha lehamtin, okay. And here רש"י
Rashi echoes what Michael was saying, or Michael echoed what רש"י Rashi
was saying, or תוספות. Tosafot. יוצא בגיט צריכה להמתין ואף על גב
דליכא לספוקי קטנה במעוברת, yotzei be-get tzericha lehamtin ve-af al gav de-leika
le-sipuki ktanah bi-me'uberet, even though we're not afraid that a קטנה ktanah
got pregnant, לא חילקו חכמים בתקנתם בנשואות. lo chilku chachamim be-takanatam bi-nesuot.
They did not make any distinctions and they said across the board
if you are really married, then even though there's no question, this
happens all the time, but anyway, happens when a couple is let's
say I don't know married and converts and they're like the woman
is past menopause, whatever, and the rabbis still say you've got to
wait three months before you can continue marrying together, or living together,
things like that. Now there is a lot of debate in the
פוסקים poskim that sometimes when it's like very demonstrably obvious, like maybe
a pregnancy test maybe counts as a substitute for three months or
clearly somebody is of the age where it's impossible or whatever, there
are some that say you don't have to, but here at
least רש"י Rashi is sort of saying expressing a sort of a
formalistic לא פלוג lo plug approach, which is I mean the גמרא
Gemara sort of saying it, that even though she's a
קטנה, ktanah, sort of the reverse of being post-menopausal, even though she's
a קטנה, ktanah, if she was married and it was a real
marriage, real, even a rabbinic marriage, then she has to wait. So
if it was never a marriage, it was retroactively uprooted because it
was מיאון, mi'un, she refused, then we know she's not pregnant, she
was never considered married, she doesn't have to wait. If however it
was a גט, get, even though it all took place as a
minor, right, so it's only a rabbinic marriage and only a rabbinic
divorce, but nevertheless she's considered divorced, rabbinically married, rabbinically divorced, and therefore
even though we know she's not pregnant she has to wait the
three months.
צריכה להמתין, tzericha lehamtin, that's going according to שמואל.
Shmuel. So שמואל Shmuel clearly distinguishes between מיאון mi'un which means it
never happened and a גט, get, even though again it's all rabbinic,
which means it happened, rabbinically there was a קידושין kiddushin and a
divorce, yes.
Can a minor do נישואין? nissuin? After נישואין? nissuin?
Well, can I mean if they started living together, yes, meaning as
long as she's still a minor, yes. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara
says but
when it was a גט get it was with נישואין, nissuin, right?
Or no, there was only a גט get from the קידושין? kiddushin?
It could have been from נישואין. nissuin. Again, standard נישואין nissuin waited
until after she was בת מצווה, bat mitzvah, but the גמרא Gemara
definitely deals with
cases where they've been living together even as a minor, which is
effectively the same as נישואין, nissuin, and that they've been having sex
and so on and even so she could still do מיאון. mi'un.
Yes.
Even according to רב Rav that he's saying it's just play acting,
if she dies, they still bury her, right?
Well, then the question is who buries her, the father or the
husband.
Doesn't רב Rav say the husband does?
I don't know, it's not clear. Let's see where the גמרא Gemara
goes with it. Okay, so this is a question about it could
be yes, it does, as long
as nothing severed the marriage, right? As long as I mean once
the marriage is severed whether through מיאון mi'un or גט, get, anyway,
let's take a look what the גמרא Gemara deals with with רב.
Rav. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says like this. מאי קמשמע לן?
mai kamashma lan? What's שמואל Shmuel teaching me? תנינא כולה, tanina kullah,
we taught all of this. הממאנת באיש, ha-mema'enet be-ish, if a woman
refuses the man that she's been this minor that she's been married
to refuses the man she's been married to, הוא מותר בקרובותיה והיא
מותרת בקרוביו, hu mutar bi-krovoteha ve-hi muteret bi-krovav, they can marry each
other's relatives, they were never married, ולא פסלה מן הכהונה, ve-lo paslah
min ha-kehunah, and she's not invalid from a כהן. kohen. נתן לה
גט, natan lah get, if he gave her a גט, get, הוא
אסור בקרובותיה והיא אסורה בקרוביו, hu assur bi-krovoteha ve-hi assurah bi-krovav, they
can't marry each other's relatives because she's considered to be divorced from
him, ופסלה מן הכהונה, u-faslah min ha-kehunah, and she's invalid for a
כהונה. kehunah. So the גמרא Gemara says what שמואל Shmuel said is
an explicit ברייתא. braita. Now of course why don't we say this
ברייתא braita contradicts רב, Rav, which it does contradict רב, Rav, because
רב Rav basically I mean you could say רב Rav is maybe
distinguishing between this and the כתובה ketubah question, but bottom line is
רב Rav had a גרסא girsa in the משנה. mishna. רב's Rav's
גרסא girsa in the משנה mishna was that even after a גט
get she doesn't get a כתובה. ketubah. So רב Rav is seeming
to claim that there's a position of תנאים tannaim out there that
even when this minor gets a גט get retroactively they were never
married. Okay, but שמואל's Shmuel's position seems to be the more standard
one and reinforced by this משנה mishna here that distinguishes between whether
she got a גט get or whether she did מיאון. mi'un. So
what is שמואל Shmuel teaching me that's not in this ברייתא? braita?
So the גמרא Gemara says צריכה להמתין ג' חדשים tzericha lehamtin gimel
chodeshim it's צריכא ליה דלא תנן. tzricha lei de-lo tnan. No, because
it wasn't explicit there about the three months thing, and you could
have thought that the three months you always have to wait, because
maybe that's just a doesn't matter whether you were married or not
married you were living together we're always going to make you wait
three months. So that was שמואל's חידוש. Shmuel's chiddush. But basically שמואל
Shmuel takes a distinction between מיאון mi'un and גט get and רב
Rav does not seem to make that distinction. So let's take a
look. לימא... leima... Yeah.
So does it feel like מיאון mi'un means that the girl didn't
want to for whatever reason, right, and גט get means that the
husband...
Yeah, I mean, but it's also a question, that's true, but it's
also a question about what act was done. מיאון miun is she
just sort of says, "I refuse you," and then she walks away,
and a גט get he actually goes...
Or after they have sex?
Could be after, but it's before sex but before בת מצווה Bat
Mitzvah she has a right to refuse. And מיאון miun is and
a גט get is he has to write a גט get and
deliver a גט get and go through that formal process.
Whether she wants to be married or not?
Sure, because the husband always has that, you know, unilateral power in
terms of the גט, get, right?
Does it disturb anybody at this table when myself and which of
my children who are eleven...
Well, yes, yes, yes, that we've been... we've been worrying about that
for the last six months. So you've got to... so you're playing
catch-up. Anyway, six years. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says like this.
לימא כתנאי... Lema kitnai... Okay, לימא
כתנאי, Lema kitnai, let's say this debate of רב Rav and שמואל,
Shmuel, which is essentially the status of this girl that got a
גט, get, whether she was considered married or not, let's say that's
a debate of תנאים. Tannaim. Here's the... here's what we got, the
ברייתא. braita. רבי אליעזר אומר, Rabbi Eliezer omer, אין מעשה קטנה כלום.
ein maaseh ketanah klum. The acts of a קטנה ketanah are meaningless.
And there ain't... meaning so the fact that she got married as
a קטנה ketanah doesn't mean anything. ואין בעלה זכאי במציאתה V'ein baalah
zakai bimtziatah and there are none of the ongoing, sort of,
privileges
and rights that exist between a married couple in this case of
the קטנה. ketanah. Okay, again, when the mother married and it's only
rabbinic. So the husband doesn't get her found objects, ולא במעשה ידיה
v'lo b'maaseh yadeha isn't entitled to her earnings, ולא בהפרת נדריה v'lo
b'hafarat nedareha doesn't annul her vows, ואינו יורשה v'eino yorshah he doesn't
inherit her, ואינו מיטמא לה v'eino mitama lah if she dies and
he's a כהן kohen he does not become טמא tameh to her.
כללו של דבר, Klalo shel davar, אינה כאשתו לכל דבר. einah k'ishto
l'chol davar.
Bottom line is even with this rabbinic institution, this קטנה ketanah is
not his wife. אלא שצריכה מיאון. Ela shetzrichah miun.
The only הלכה halacha is, is that she... if she wants to
walk away, she needs to do this act of מיאון. miun. Or
said another way, if she doesn't do an act of מיאון miun
and she stays with him after בת מצווה, Bat Mitzvah, then she'll
be his wife. But while she's a קטנה, ketanah, we're not recognizing
this as a marriage. We're recognizing this as whatever it is, some,
you know...
If she wants to get out? Or if he didn't feed her?
Well, the father... yeah, well that's a good point because presumably it
doesn't speak about whether he's חייב במזונותיה, chayav bimzonoteha, right? Because probably
one of the reasons that the mother would marry her off was...
was that she wouldn't have to support her or something. So that's
a good point. The... the other reason is just that she shouldn't
be taken advantage of is another reason the mother would marry her
off. Okay, so anyway, but he says is this is not really
a marriage. Okay, she's a קטנה, ketanah, it was done by the
mothers, it's not a marriage. The הלכה halacha though is, is that
either... is that she does מיאון miun before she's בת מצווה, Bat
Mitzvah, and then she walks away. And if she doesn't do מיאון
miun before she's בת מצווה Bat Mitzvah and stays with him, then
she'll be married. But right now it's really not a marriage.
This is a
simple statement?
Yep. Okay, so that's what he says.
But if she had a father we wouldn't be in this situation.
Right, because then it would be biblically binding. רבי יהושע אומר, Rabbi
Yehoshua omer, מעשה קטנה כלום. maaseh ketanah klum. Of course... it is
meaningful. It's interesting that it calls it מעשה קטנה maaseh ketanah because
it's really done by the mother. But okay, it is meaningful. ובעלה
זכאי במציאתה U'vaalah zakai bimtziatah he's entitled to her found objects, ובמעשה
ידיה u'v'maaseh yadeha and her earnings, ובהפרת נדריה v'v'hafarat nedareha and he
annuls her vows, ויורשה v'yorshah and he inherits her, ומיטמא לה v'mitama
lah
and he becomes טמא tameh to her. כללו של דבר, Klalo shel
davar, הרי היא כאשתו לכל דבר. harei hi k'ishto l'chol davar. She...
she is considered his wife, at least rabbinically. Okay, אלא שיוצאה במיאון,
ela sheyotzah b'miun,
except for one difference is that she's entitled to do מיאון miun
and a person who's normally a wife... a woman who's normally a
wife is not entitled to do מיאון miun but she actually has
to get a גט. get. Okay, so there's a very profound difference
about how much you see this as... as really being a type
of a marriage. Okay, so now let's see what the גמרא Gemara
says. So, לימא רב דאמר כרבי אליעזר. lema Rav d'amar k'Rabbi Eliezer.
רב Rav
who says that even when she gets a גט, get, he doesn't
recognize her as having been married and basically says she doesn't get
a כתובה, ketubah, that's like רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer who says they...
she was never really married. ושמואל דאמר כרבי יהושע U'Shmuel d'amar k'Rabbi
Yehoshua and שמואל Shmuel says like רבי יהושע Rabbi Yehoshua that she
was married, okay, and only a מיאון miun would undermine it but
and... without a מיאון miun she basically is married. So the גמרא
Gemara says, so sounds like it's very much falling along those lines.
So the גמרא Gemara says אליבא דרבי אליעזר כולי עלמא לא פליגי.
aliba d'Rabbi Eliezer kulei alma la pligi. You're right. According to רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer nobody debates. According to רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer he's
very clear they're not really married. And since they're not really married,
obviously she's not going to get... she's not going to get a
כתובה ketubah if he gives her a גט. get. He says all
along it wasn't a marriage. It's not like there was something that's
then being reversed. All along there wasn't a marriage and therefore of
course there's no... there's no כתובה. ketubah.
Remind me again why would she need a גט get in that
case if she wasn't really married?
Well, the... the Rabbis required her to, you know, again, it's like
the Rabbis created this institution. What are we calling it? So רבי
אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer says we're not calling it marriage, we're calling it,
I don't know, pre-marriage or something.
It's a rabbinic institution?
Yeah, it's a rabbinic גט. get. Not a תורה? Torah?
Oh, not a תורה, Torah,
yeah, right, because it's only a rabbinic marriage. So... so רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua says we're calling it a marriage, which could be reversed
if she does מיאון. miun. If she does a גט get it's
not reversed, it's just ended. Okay, but רבי אליעזר Rabbi Eliezer is
saying we're not calling it a marriage, we're calling it, I don't
know, a pre-marriage. Okay, so if you don't do anything about it
and she grows up and is בת מצווה Bat Mitzvah and stays
with him, they're married. But if you sever it, either by her
doing מיאון miun or him giving a גט, get, then nothing happened.
But in the interim, it's not yet... it's not really a marriage.
So according to him, of course she doesn't get a כתובה. ketubah.
אליבא דרבי אליעזר Aliba deRabbi Eliezer though כולי עלמא לא פליגי, kulei
alma lo pligi,
nobody disagrees. Where was I? אליבא דכולי עלמא לא פליגי. Aliba d'kulei
alma lo pligi. אליבא דכולי עלמא לא פליגי. Aliba d'kulei alma lo
pligi. כי פליגי אליבא דרבי יהושע. Ki pligi aliba deRabbi Yehoshua.
According to Rabbi Yehoshua says that they were married. So then they
were married she should get a גט, Get, so שמואל Shmuel to
Rabbi Yehoshua, שמואל Shmuel goes like the simple reason of Rabbi Yehoshua,
they were married so she gets a גט Get she should get
a כתובה. Ketubah. ורב V'Rav and רב Rav would tell you, עד
כאן לא קאמר רבי יהושע התם, ad kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Yehoshua
hatam, when does Rabbi Yehoshua say that they're married and he had
all of these sort of you know privileges exist? אלא, Ela, you're
going to enjoy this, מדידה לדידיה, mididah l'didei, when he gets things
from her. So he gets all of these benefits. That's, to that
extent they're married. Okay, אבל מדידיה לדידה, aval mididei l'didah, but
that it should actually be something that she gets from him, so
that they get divorced and he actually has to pay the כתובה,
Ketubah, לא, lo, no, that she's not entitled to. He's only, he's
entitled to benefiting from her, she's not entitled to benefiting from him.
What is the logic for this? So let's take a look
at רש״י, Rashi, okay?
Okay, so רש״י, Rashi, the first point you have to know is
that do you see where the רש״י Rashi says כי פליגי אליבא
דרבי יהושע ki pligi aliba deRabbi Yehoshua about ten lines down in
the inner line? So the first thing you have to know is
conceptually why we understood that there was a need for this. The
need for this institution is not seen as financial. If you take
a look at רש״י Rashi he says, he says, דתקנו חכמים
נישואין
detaknu
chachamim nisuin it's about five lines down in the inner lines, ליתומה
על ידי אמה ואחיה להנאתה ולטובתה תיקנו, leyetomah al yedei imah ve'acheha
lahana'atah uletovatah tiknu,
they did it to protect for her benefit. What's her benefit? כדאמרינן
ביבמות פרק חרש, kedamrinan beYevamot perek cheresh, שמא ינהגו בה מנהג הפקר,
shema yinhagu bah minhag hefker, שאין קטנה יודעת לשמור עצמה מלהתפתות. she'ein
ketanah yode'at lishmor atzmah me'lehitpatot.
We were concerned that people would seduce her, although it's true she
was very young, but I guess that was society. And therefore, they
wanted to marry off to at least have a man to protect
her now that there was no father alive. And that was understood,
that was what was understood, so not to financially provide for her,
that's going to be relevant for part two, but the primary institution
was to protect her from being seduced. So therefore, let's see what
he says, hold on, let's see what he says.
So he says like this: עד כאן לא קאמר רבי יהושע ad
kan lo ka'amar Rabbi Yehoshua he says, so again this is like
I don't know what to tell you, it's like 15 lines down,
five lines above the תוספות רי״ד, Tosafot Rid, he says, רבי יהושע
Rabbi Yehoshua only says דמהני נישואין d'mahanei nisuin אלא מדידה לדידיה. ela
mididah l'didei.
He's entitled to her earnings, כגון ירושתה, kegon yerushatah, inheriting her, ומעשה
ידיה ומציאתה, uma'aseh yadeha umtzi'atah, שיהיו לבעל. she'yihyu laba'al.
Why? Why is he getting all that stuff? כי היכי דלא לימנעו
מלמיסבה. ki heichi delo limnu mil'misbah.
You have to give him some incentive for marrying this minor woman.
Like he's going to marry her, right, and not get any of
the like financial benefits that come through marriage? So what's in it
for him? So therefore clearly you have to continue to have those
privileges and benefits that he has. כי היכי דלא לימנעו מלמיסבה. ki
heichi delo limnu mil'misbah. Okay, now אבל, aval, now the רש״י Rashi
right near the תוספות רי״ד, Tosafot Rid, אבל מדידיה לדידה, aval mididei
l'didah, כגון כתובתה ותנאי כתובתה, kegon ktubatah utnai ktubatah, רש״י Rashi doesn't
say anything else. Okay,
but basically what רש״י Rashi is saying is is that what we
have is a man is marrying this minor. Now again we're all
like rightfully offended that you know sometimes the גמרא Gemara suggests that
they're having sex. But the reality is is that like we've learned
in other גמרות, Gemarot, they you know you really wait for the
נישואין nisuin until after she's בת מצווה, Bat Mitzvah, you know. The
reality is is that I think we can assume that it's rare
that they're actually really you know really having sex and living together
and so on. So the question is what's in it, why marrying
why the mother wants to marry this young girl off is clear,
like you know, a, it's another mouth to feed and b, it's
like a you know it's they're afraid that she's going to be
taken advantage of, there's no man to protect her. But why would
the man want to marry marry this six-year-old girl, right? What so
I mean if let's put it this way, especially if a, they're
not living together they wouldn't really be living together and b, if
if he doesn't have any of the normal privileges you know that
that come through marriage in terms of financial privileges.
And there's no guarantee, that's another good point, more than if the
father marries her off where he knows that it's a lot that's
an excellent point, if the father marries her off it's a lock
it's a done deal it's locked in. Here she could walk away
at any time. So we're saying minimally we've got to give him
the normal financial privileges that come through marriage. But we don't have
to do it in the other direction because give her the privileges
because he's the guy we have to incentivize. So if he's the
guy we have to incentivize,
right, we're going to give him the privileges without the costs, without
the fact that he would have to pay the כתובה. Ketubah. So
that's the explanation of רב. Rav. It could go well be they're
considered to be married, but nevertheless רב Rav says I don't disagree
in general. In general, one minute, in general, I agree. With a
תנא tanna with a גט, Get, she was considered to have been
married. All the discussions you had about can be marry the relatives,
is she פסולה לכהונה, psulah lechuna, I agree with all of that.
She was considered to be married. What I'm saying, says רב, Rav,
is she's not entitled to the. כתובה. ksuva. This is a particular
institution which the Rabbis created that we have to incentivize the man
to enter into, and the way we're going to incentivize the man
is to say it's not going to come with the cost of
the כתובה ksuva until after she's an adult. But while she's a
minor, and I think Dov made the real point, and she can
always walk away and you don't even know that you've got the
deal done, then you're not going to have to pay the כתובה.
ksuva. Okay, first Dov, yes.
Just to clarify, therefore this exercising the right of מיאון Mi'un only
applies if there's no father in the picture, right? If there's a
mother and a brother marrying her off. And what you're suggesting might
look like this eight-year-old girl moving into the house of an older
man who's taking care of her as a younger girl until she
gets old enough for him to literally marry.
Right, although let's—although
without pretending that there weren't cases where they were sleeping together because
it was clear in our משנה, Mishnah, right. Oh, that's different, okay.
Exactly, exactly, yes.
Two questions.
One:
Why does he just marry the mother?
That was a—yes. My
second question is we're talking about a Jewish society. And I know
I'm so naive for a woman my age it's ridiculous, but we
are worried about Jewish men seducing eight-year-old girls and nine-year-old and ten-year-old
girls?
We're really worried—I mean what, I don't know, fourteen-year-old boys maybe?
I mean you want to go, there's something fundamentally wrong with society
if that's the case. That's really seriously wrong, that's one. And and
two: Let's say this eight-year-old, nine-year-old girl is still living at home.
Right. How does somebody know she's married in quotes?
Well, that's the whole point, she wouldn't be living at home. She
mostly would live in with the guy—moving in with the guy. Whether
they're having sex or not is a different question. But that's part
of the whole point I think.
Didn't you say that she could even not be living with him?
Yeah, well, she could not be having sex with him. I mean,
I think right, I I think that based on the realities of
why you would do this she basically would move in with him.
Then he would pay for her and then he would be around
to pay for her food and be around to protect her and
so on. That's what I think. But in terms of the issue,
I agree, like for us to think about you know this issue—first
of all, you know things were different in those days, you know,
and like there was no childhood anyway. You know, you pretty much,
you know, five years old you gotta get out and get a
job. What are you doing still being around the house? I mean,
people grew up a lot quicker those days. And I think that
the interesting thing is that the Rabbis weren't living in a little
castle in the sky. The very fact that they recognize the possibility
that there could be people seducing an eight-year-old girl, you know, for—I
mean it's like—they were aware that even though they're like dealing with
people that should be keeping הלכה Halacha and whatever, you know, and
maybe there were also people that were, you know, that you engage
in society that don't keep הלכה Halacha or whatever, but it
wasn't purely a Jewish society.
It wasn't purely a Jewish society, but I think there's something important
about the fact that they're not that they're being realistic. All right.
Am I correct—correct me if I'm wrong, you're talking about the fifth,
the sixth century in Baghdad, or what was going to become Baghdad.
Right, well they're trying to explain the basis of what was going
on in the משנה. Mishnah. All right. Okay, moving on.
Moving on. I gotta get a whistle. Okay. Moving on, ולא בלאות.
valo blat. אמר ליה רב הונא בר חייא לרב כהנא: Amar le
Rav Huna bar Chiya le Rav Kahana:
So this is that she does not when she walks away in
all these cases, either because she was never married or because of
this penalizing because it was a rabbinically forbidden marriage, she does not
get the worn-out things. Now again, the worn-out things, yeah presumably I
don't know exactly. Anyway, the worn-out things could either mean, as תוספות
Tosafot says, she doesn't get reimbursed for any of her property that
was consumed
during the period. Or רש"י Rashi says it means that she doesn't
take the property even that's around that's now been somewhat worn out.
But it seems more like תוספות, Tosafot, that she doesn't get reimbursed
for any of her property that was consumed. But let's take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. אמר ליה רב הונא בר חייא לרב
כהנא. Amar le Rav Huna bar Chiya le Rav Kahana. So רב
הונא בר חייא Rav Huna bar Chiya says to רב כהנא, Rav
Kahana, אמרתון משמיה דשמואל, Amartun mishme de-Shmuel, you told us in the
name of שמואל: Shmuel: לא שנו אלא נכסי מלוג. Lo shanu ela
nichsei milog.
When is that true that she doesn't get reimbursed, I'll read it
תוספות's Tosafot way,
only by if the נכסי מלוג nichsei milog were used up. Now
again normally that's talking about a land, so you don't really use
up land, but it really could be anything. So she brings in
property into the estate and again remember there are two things. One
is the stuff she retains title to, which isn't mentioned in the
כתובה, ksuva, it's just property she owns. She had a Ferrari, she
comes with the Ferrari into the marriage and she—no no no well
we won't—we're not talking about the תקנה, Takkanah, she brings it into
the marriage. That's נכסי מלוג, nichsei milog, it's still hers. Okay, the
הלכה Halacha though is that אוכל פירות, ochel peirot, so he might
get the right to drive the Ferrari, but she still—but it's still
hers. Okay, so what happens if in the course of the marriage
it gets destroyed, does he have to total it or whatever? Okay,
so it was hers. Does she—in a normal marriage if she would
get divorced then he would have to reimburse her. That was her
property, okay, and she comes in with and goes out with it,
especially but might depend on whose fault it was, but let's say
he—let's say he sold off the Ferrari or something whatever, it was
hers and she's entitled to be reimbursed. Okay, נכסי צאן ברזל nichsei
tzon barzel is that
is what she brought in as a dowry that she actually signed
over to him and was mentioned in the כתובה, Ketubah, okay, so
he gets, he says fine, you come in with your Ferrari but
I demand a Jaguar for your dowry. So she brings that in
and she gives him the Jaguar. Okay, so that's the dowry, that's
the נכסי צאן ברזל. Nichsei Tzon Barzel. So that he actually has
title to. The only הלכה halacha is that if they get divorced,
then he has to give it back to her or give her
the cost of it. Okay, so that's the difference. נכסי צאן ברזל,
Nichsei Tzon Barzel, נכסי מלוג Nichsei Milog she retained title to,
נכסי צאן ברזל Nichsei Tzon Barzel he was given over to him,
he got title to. Now it says that when she walks away
in these cases, when there was no marriage, let's focus on those
cases, okay, that לא שנו, Lo Shanu, that she doesn't get anything
that was destroyed in the marriage. So during the marriage, both the
Ferrari and the Jaguar were totaled. Okay, and whatever, he sold them.
He's now very upset.
She's upset. She doesn't walk away with anything. Okay, so let's take
a look. So אמר להו משמיה דשמואל, Amar Lehu Mishmei DeShmuel, you
told us in the name of שמואל, Shmuel, לא שנו אלא נכסי
מלוג, Lo Shanu Ella Nichsei Milog,
when is it that she doesn't walk away with getting reimbursed in
terms of the נכסי מלוג, Nichsei Milog, which is stuff she always
had title to, the Ferrari, אבל נכסי צאן ברזל, Aval Nichsei Tzon
Barzel, the Jaguar, אית לה, Iit Lah, she does walk away. Now
that's bizarre because the נכסי מלוג Nichsei Milog is stuff she always
had title to, so that's the stuff that you would think that
she's more entitled to walk away with. So let's take a look.
Okay,
הוי בה רב פפא, Hevi Bah Rav Pappa, רב פפא Rav Pappa
asked, אהיי, Ahei, on which case of the משנה Mishna is this
going on? אילימא אמהמנת, Ileima Amemanes, the young girl who walks away,
so he says I don't get it, אי דאיתנהו, Ei De'itnehu, if
the property is still around, אידי ואידי שקלה, Idy Ve'idy Shakla, she
should walk away, right, there was retroactively no marriage, so she should
just walk away with it, it was always hers, ואי דליתנהו, Ve'ei
De'leitnehu, if they've been totaled or sold off or whatever, אידי ואידי
לא שקלה, Idy Ve'idy Lo Shakla, she shouldn't get either. Now why
should she not get either if there retroactively was no marriage? So
the assumption is that even though retroactively there was no marriage, we
only found out retroactively. During the time, there was presumed to be
a marriage and he was at least entitled to sell it off.
So since at that time, at least for the נכסי צאן ברזל,
Nichsei Tzon Barzel, not clear why the נכסי מלוג, Nichsei Milog, so
since in the time when they were, when it was at stake,
it was his property and he sold it off and he pocketed
the money. Now all she has on him is she says, oh,
but you owe me that money because it's in the כתובה. Ketubah.
So he says, what כתובה? Ketubah? We were never married, so there's
never really any entitlement of the כתובה. Ketubah. Okay, but then retroactively
it was my property you sold off. No, cause at the time
I sold it, it was my property. So therefore, that's the sort
of logic. When he sold it, he was entitled to sell it,
it was his property. Now she wants to collect it because the
כתובה Ketubah says if she gets divorced she's entitled to take that
money out, but she wasn't divorced, there was never a marriage. So
that's the logic of the נכסי צאן ברזל. Nichsei Tzon Barzel. It's
harder to understand the נכסי מלוג, Nichsei Milog, because the נכסי מלוג
Nichsei Milog he didn't have an option, a right to sell. So
it's not obvious why that she's not entitled to be reimbursed for.
Let's just bracket that cause we'll see what the גמרא Gemara is
going to say in a minute, it'll essentially say that by the
אילונית, Aylonit,
it's a flaw that there's no legal instrument to correct for that.
I understand that. I understand that.
Again,
there's things that are consumable.
Right, let's keep on going everybody. It says like this, אלא אילונית,
Ella Aylonit, how about the case of the אילונית? Aylonit? Same question.
That was a מקח טעות. Mekach Ta'ut. Okay, אי דאיתנהו, Ei De'itnehu,
if they're around and it was all a מקח טעות, Mekach Ta'ut,
אידי ואידי שקלה, Idy Ve'idy Shakla, let her walk away with both.
אי דליתנהו, Ei De'leitnehu, if they've been consumed or destroyed or sold
off, איפכא מיבעי ליה, Ipcha Miba'ei Lei, it should be the reverse.
What's the reverse? נכסי מלוג דברשותה קיימי, Nichsei Milog DeVirshuta Kaimi, so
it turns out they were never married, so she says look look
hubby, look buddy, that Ferrari, that was always mine and you shouldn't
have sold it. So it turns out retroactively we were never married,
so retroactively you sold something that was mine, you need to reimburse
me for it, that was mine. אית לה, Iit Lah, so that
she should be reimbursed for. נכסי צאן ברזל, Nichsei Tzon Barzel, the
Jaguar, which at the time we thought we were married, ודלאו ברשותה
קיימי, Vedelav Birshuta Kaimi, at that time it wasn't mine, it was
presumed to be yours, לית לה, Leit Lah, that would make sense
that I can't get reimbursed for. Okay, and that's so why the
גמרא Gemara assumed that by the case of ממאנת Memanes she should
not be
reimbursed for either is not clear to me, but what it's saying
here makes a lot of sense is like look, if it turns
out they were never married, so then if the stuff is still
around, walk away with it. And if the stuff isn't around, then
the question is was he entitled to sell it, while they were
married,
during that past period when they thought they were married. If he
was entitled to sell it, right, then she has no right now
to demand to be paid for it. If he wasn't entitled to
sell it because it was her under her title, then she should.
be able to get paid for it. But שמואל Shmuel says the
reverse. שמואל Shmuel says the
נכסי מלוג Nichsei Milug is what she doesn't get reimbursed for and
the נכסי צאן ברזל Nichsei Tzon Barzel is what she does get
reimbursed for. So that doesn't make any sense. So the גמרא Gemara
says אלא אשניה. Ella Ashniah.
So we're talking about the case where it's the rabbinically forbidden marriage.
So still, how does it make sense? So here's the logic: דקנסו
רבנן לדידה בדידיה ולדידיה בדידה. Deknasu Rabbanan Ledida Bedidei Uledidei Bedida.
So sort of we sort of fine everybody by reversing everything. Again,
I don't really understand it. We want them to be married, so
the way we're going to stop them from being married is we're
going to say everybody loses out. Okay, so now you get divorced.
Oh, you should be taking away
your נכסי מלוג, Nichsei Milug, because that's the stuff you always had
title to. Ha, we're going to take away something that you deserve,
and we're going to say you don't get back your נכסי מלוג.
Nichsei Milug. Now, on the other hand, you shouldn't be taking away
your נכסי צאן ברזל, Nichsei Tzon Barzel, because that was his and
he had title to it. Ha, we're going to take that away
from him and give it to the woman in order to... everybody
gets something taken away from them. Which is an interesting psychology because
you could have sort of said to even it out and it's
all a question of which is more. But you know, the point
is, one minute, that's mine, I'm entitled to it. So the very
fact that we're taking away something that you're entitled to, that's going
to serve as some disincentive. So logically you're right, she should walk
away with her נכסי מלוג Nichsei Milug and he should walk away
with the נכסי צאן ברזל, Nichsei Tzon Barzel, but because we don't
like this, we rip away from everybody what's theirs and give it
to the other person. Go figure that out. Okay, keep on going.
People are happy?
People, I know. Let's just move on. A minor can have property.
She can be given... she can have inherited it, yes, I want
to give her property. Okay, alright. Everybody, we're way behind. Okay.
We're going to have a discussion group after the דף Daf where
everybody can get out all of their issues. Alright, now we say
like
this: אמר רב שימי בר אשי שמע מינה מדרב כהנא. Amar Rav
Shimi Bar Ashi Shma Mina Miderav Kahana. We see from רב כהנא
Rav Kahana אייתי לה גלימא, Aitei Lah Glima, that since we're talking
here about consumables because the thing isn't around anymore, right? That's the
example I gave you. So what does it... so that tells us
something. If somebody brings in a cloak into the marriage, then קרנא
הוי, Karna Havei, then it's still considered to be a principal, meaning
and therefore something she has title to and therefore something she's entitled
to take out of the marriage. Okay, why? What else would it
be? ולא מיכסי ליה ואזיל עד דבלי. Velo Michsi Lei Va'azil Ad
Debali. He can't go ahead and use it up until he wears
it out. Okay, if we basically said, here she brings a cloak,
right? A Ferrari's a little bit more durable presumably than this cloak.
Here she brings this cloak into the marriage. So how do we
conceptualize it? Do we basically say that, okay, she has title to
the cloak and he gets the פירות? Peirot? So he's going to
get the פירות, Peirot, and he's going to keep on wearing it
and wearing it and wearing it until it wears out. But fine,
that was just its use, he was entitled to the use and
he doesn't owe her anything. So that's one way of conceptualizing it.
In that case, we wouldn't be having our discussion, because she can't
say give me back the principal. There is no principal, I got
the פירות Peirot and in the process of using the פירות, Peirot,
the
principal disappeared. But there was no
real principal really to talk about. All there was in the cloak
was ten years of פירות. Peirot. There was no conceptualized separate principal
that's going to be durable. There was just ten years of פירות
Peirot and it's all mine. But we didn't say that. We say
that when she walks away, in principle she's entitled to take back...
she's entitled to take back the principal. So we conceptualize this not
as something with ten years of פירות, Peirot, but we conceptualize this
as something with a principal, with a קרן. Keren. Okay, ולא מיכסי
ליה ואזיל עד דבלי. Velo Michsi Lei Va'azil Ad Debali. He can't
wear it till it gets worn out.
Basically, what he has to do is he has to take the
money, sell it, take the money, and buy something that is durable
and buy land and then get the פירות Peirot from the land.
Okay, but if you're saying now that he's wearing... ולא מיכסי לה?
Velo Michsi Lah?
לה Lah is the cloak.
Okay, so she can't wear it either, the cloak?
No, well,
I don't know, she has to transfer it into something that has
principal and fruit. Okay, עד דבלי. Ad Debali. ואמר רב נחמן פירא
הוי. Veamar Rav Nachman Peira Havei. But רב נחמן Rav Nachman says
that it is פירא Peira and that basically he's entitled to all
of it. When she brings in the cloak or the Ferrari, it's
basically ten years of פירא, Peira, there is no conceptual קרן Keren
here. So the גמרא Gemara says, no, דרב נחמן פליגא. Derav Nachman
Peliga. That would disagree with what we said. Okay, so basically we're
talking about she doesn't get בלאות. Blaot. בלאות Blaot means she doesn't
get reimbursed for the consumables that were used up. Okay, and here's
the basic point, right? She brings in consumables into the marriage that
she had title to, or that he got as the dowry: the
cloak and the Ferrari and the dishes and all these things that
in the course of their use they got used up. And the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, they got used up, he has no principal.
No, the implication is that a normal woman when she would get
divorced would be entitled to take back out the principal even though
these are consumables. So that's the point. The point is you see
from this that in... when you bring something into the marriage, even
if it's a consumable, conceptually we don't think of it as just
ten years of פירות. peiros. We think of it as a principal
that you're going to be entitled to take back out, and in
order maybe to make that happen we would sell it and transfer
it to something that really was durable. Okay, but therefore, so in
this special case she doesn't get reimbursed for it. But in a
normal case, even though it got destroyed through the process of use,
she would get reimbursed.
Only if he uses it, right? Like if she comes in with
her clothes, I'm not going to have to pay for the clothes
she wore into the marriage? Right, correct.
Okay, אין לה כתובה. ein lah kesuvah. אמר
שמואל, amar Shmuel, now לא שנו, lo shanu, this הלכה halachah that
these women don't get a כתובה, kesuvah, okay, לא שנו אלא מנה
מאתים. lo shanu ela maneh masayim. All we're talking here about is
about the base כתובה, kesuvah, אבל תוספת יש להן. aval tosefes yesh
lahen. Actually, they are entitled to the תוספת tosefes because the תוספת
tosefes was not rabbinically instituted, it was a gift. And he basically
said, I love you so much I'm also going to add a
certain amount to the כתובה. kesuvah. So interestingly, all these women, even
though retroactively they were never married, he still gave them this gift.
And as רש"י Rashi says, they've still been having sex, and
maybe she's walking away with nothing, maybe she'll feel very used out
of that whole process. So even if it wasn't a marriage, this
is a gift that he gave her just for the fact that
they will
be in practice man and wife, whether rabbinically or not, whether that
would actually be recognized as a marriage in the end or not.
Well, and some of them haven't been having sex though.
Well, that's true. תניא נמי הכי, tanya nami hachi, we've taught similarly,
נשים שאמרו חכמים אין להן כתובה, nashim she'amru chachamim ein lahen kesuvah,
the women when the משנה mishna says אין להן כתובה, ein lahen
kesuvah, so what does אין להן כתובה ein lahen kesuvah mean? כגון
הממאנת וחברותיה, kegon hamema'enes vachaviroseha,
like the woman who refuses and her pals, the שניה shniya and
the אילונית, ailonis, so those women, אין להם מנה מאתים. ein lahem
maneh masayim. What it means is that they don't have the hundred
or two hundred, אבל תוספת יש להם, aval tosefes yesh lahem, they
have the additional amount that the husband adds on and was not
rabbinically required. נשים שאמרו חכמים יוצאות בלא כתובה, nashim she'amru chachamim yotzos
belo kesuvah, however, if a משנה mishna doesn't just say they don't
get a כתובה, kesuvah, if a משנה mishna says they must be
divorced without the rights of a כתובה, kesuvah, which means that the
rabbis are really sort of saying that this is an unacceptable marriage
and we're going to force you to get a divorce, so that
type of a case is much more censorious and therefore what we
would say is, כגון, kegon, what's an example of those? עוברת על
דת וחברותיה, overes al das vachaviroseha, the woman who goes against the
norms of הלכה halachah and Jewish women in a way that really
injures the marriage, flirting with other men, not covering her head, feeding
him not kosher food, those types of cases, אין להם תוספת. ein
lahem tosefes. We strip her of all of her rights and she
doesn't even get the תוספת, tosefes, the additional, וכל שכן מנה מאתים.
vechol sheken maneh masayim. Okay, now, והיוצאת משום שם רע, vehayotzos mishum
shem ra, a woman who is being divorced because of a suspicion
of adultery,
נוטלת מה שלפניה ויוצאת. noteles mah shelefaneha veyotzos. So obviously presumably she
doesn't get the
מנה מאתים maneh masayim and she doesn't get the תוספת tosefes or
whatever, but she takes whatever property is still physically present in front
of her and she walks out with it. And this was the
point that סופר Sofer was making before. Before when we were talking
about the בלאות, bla'os, we were talking about can she get reimbursed
for property that was consumed? You used up
my Ferrari until you drove it into the ground. Can you, can't
you get paid for it? Here, the stuff is still there. The
Ferrari is still in the garage. Her clothes are still in her
closet. So even though this woman has possibly committed adultery, which is
like the worst offense in terms of a basis for divorce,
nevertheless, she's still able to take the clothes out of her closet.
She's still able to leave with the stuff that she owned and
take that out of the house, or that she brought or that
she had title to. מסייע ליה לרב הונא, mesayeya lay l'Rav Huna,
this supports רב הונא, Rav Huna, דאמר רב הונא, d'amar Rav Huna,
רב הונא Rav Huna says, זינתה לא הפסידה בלאותיה. zinsah lo hifsidah
bla'oseha. If a woman commits adultery, she still does not give up
the right to her worn-out clothing, בלאותיה קיימין, bla'oseha kayamin, that are
still physically present. תני תנא קמיה דרב נחמן, tani tana kamei d'Rav
Nachman, a tana taught before רב נחמן, Rav Nachman, זינתה הפסידה בלאותיה
קיימין. zinsah hifsidah bla'oseha kayamin. No, if she commits adultery she loses
even her clothing, even the clothes she has in her closet. אמר
ליה, amar lay, אם היא זינתה, im hi zinsah, if she committed
adultery, כליה מי זנאי, kalei mi zanai, her clothing didn't commit adultery?
Which is of course a funny thing to say, but we're penalizing
her, but it's a little רחמנות, rachmanus, who cares? Even if she
committed adultery she does not leave naked, she's able to take her
clothes out with her. תני, tani, we taught in a ברייתא, braisa,
לא הפסידה בלאותיה קיימין, lo hifsidah bla'oseha kayamin, she does not lose
her clothes that are still around. אמר רבה בר בר חנה אמר
רבי יוחנן, amar Rabbah bar bar Chana amar Rabbi Yochanan, זו דברי
רבי מנחם סתימאה, zu divrei Rabbi Menachem stima'ah, this slight that we
taught earlier that says she does lose it was taught a סתם
ברייתא stam braisa in the name, but that was really the position
of רבי מנחם, Rabbi Menachem, אבל חכמים אומרים, aval chachamim omrim, but
the sages say, זינתה לא הפסידה בלאותיה קיימין, zinsah lo hifsidah bla'oseha
kayamin, even if she commits adultery she does not forfeit
her clothing. Okay, and her these things that she owns that is
still around.
Yeah, anything that was essentially קרן keren that she had title to
and that is still physically present. Okay, אם תחילה נשאת, im techilah
nisays, if he married the אילונית ailonis knowing she was an אילונית,
ailonis, she is entitled to the כתובה. kesuvah. אמר רב הונא, amar
Rav Huna, אילונית אישה ואינה אישה, ailonis isha ve'einah isha, אלמנה אישה
גמורה. almanah isha gemurah. Now אישה isha does not mean a woman
here, it means a wife. An אילונית ailonis in some ways is
considered his wife and not, a widow who marries a
כהן. kohen. is fully considered his wife. What does this mean? איילונית
aylonit אשה ואינה אשה. ishah ve'eina ishah. Okay, it just feels like
it's also a play on the idea that this is a woman
that has some male characteristics, but anyway, his wife and not his
wife in the following way: It depends on the circumstance. הכיר בה,
hekir bah, if he knew that she was an איילונית, aylonit, then
she is his wife.
יש לה כתובה. yesh lah ketubah. לא הכיר בה, lo hekir bah,
if he didn't realize she was an איילונית, aylonit, אין לה כתובה,
ein lah ketubah, she doesn't. אלמנה, almanah, however, the widow marrying a
כהן גדול, kohen gadol, אשה גמורה, ishah gemurah, whether he knew or
not, יש לה כתובה, yesh lah ketubah, because basically we say it's
not a מקח טעות, mekach ta'ut, it might not be allowed, but
it wasn't a מקח טעות, mekach ta'ut, so either way it's a
marriage. Okay, רבי יהודה אומר, Rabbi Yehuda omer, now רבי יהודה Rabbi
Yehuda says: אחת זו ואחת זו, achat zu ve'achat zu, either case,
אשה ואינה אשה, ishah ve'eina ishah, it depends on the circumstances. הכיר
בה, hekir bah, יש לה כתובה, yesh lah ketubah, if he knew
what he was getting himself into then she gets a כתובה. ketubah.
לא הכיר בה, lo hekir bah, if he didn't, אין לה כתובה,
ein lah ketubah, because we could say that if the כהן kohen
did not know that he was marrying a woman forbidden to him,
he didn't really want to marry her. So maybe it was a
מקח טעות, mekach ta'ut, maybe it wasn't a binding marriage at all,
even though it was a binding marriage, he wouldn't you know, she's
not entitled to a כתובה. ketubah. Okay, so if he didn't know,
then she should not be entitled to a כתובה. ketubah. מיתיבי, metivei,
I'll ask you: כנסה בחזקת שהיא כן ונמצאת שהיא כן, kinsah bechezkat
shehi ken venimtzat shehi ken, if he married her thinking she was
one way, realizing what she was, and that's what she was, thinking
she was an אלמנה almanah and she was an אלמנה, almanah, יש
לה כתובה, yesh lah ketubah, she gets a כתובה. ketubah. So the
implication is that's only because he knew what he was getting himself
into. הסתמא, hastama, if there was nothing said and he didn't realize
what she was, then אין לה כתובה. ein lah ketubah. The implication
is, if it turned out she was an אלמנה, almanah, turns out
then she doesn't get a כתובה, ketubah, that's what it sounds like.
So you see that argues against the one that said that it
doesn't matter. And he says: No, לא תימא הסתמא אין לה כתובה,
lo teima hastama ein lah ketubah, don't read it that way, to
say that if he wasn't aware and it turned out she was
forbidden that she doesn't get a כתובה. ketubah. He doesn't. אלא אימא,
ela eima, you should read the following: כנסה בחזקת שאינה כן, kinsah
bechezkat she'eina ken, if she explicitly said to him: "I'm not an
אלמנה, almanah, I'm not a גרושה", gerusha ונמצאת שהיא כן, venimtzat she'hiken,
and then it turned out she was. So it wasn't just a
misunderstanding, there was deception. Okay, if she deceived him, then in that
case
אימא כתובה. eima ketubah. But, אבל סתמא מאי, aval stama mai, what
would you tell me if nothing was said? There was just an
assumption and then it turned out he was wrong. אית לה, islah,
you tell me that she still does get a כתובה? ketubah? אדיתני
בחזקת שהיא כן ונמצאת שהיא כן, aditany bechezkat shehi ken venimtzat shehi
ken, then why did it only say that she gets a כתובה
ketubah when he knew that this was the situation and it was
the situation?
יש לה כתובה. yesh lah ketubah. לישמעינן תהא ביקו חידוש, lishma’inan tehei
biku chiddush, סתמא, stama, even if there was nothing said, and he
was just making some assumption and then, and then, and then it
turned out she was an אלמנה, almanah, tell me that in that
case she gets a כתובה. ketubah. וכל שכן, v'chol sheken, and certainly
if it was said explicitly that she was an
אלמנה. almanah. ועוד, ve'od, number two, תני, tani, we have a ברייתא,
braisa, it says it's explicit, it says כנסה בידוע ונמצאת בידוע, kinsah
biyeduah venimtzas biyeduah, he married her knowing she was an אלמנה, almanah,
turned out she was an אלמנה, almanah, יש לה כתובה, yesh lah
ketubah, she gets a כתובה. ketubah. כנסה סתם, kinsah stam, if he
married her without saying anything explicit,
nothing having been said explicitly, and it turned out she was an
אלמנה almanah or גרושה, gerusha, whatever she was forbidden to him as
a כהן, kohen, אין לה כתובה. ein lah ketubah. So you see
it's very clear. תיובתא דרב הונא תיובתא. tyuvta deRav Huna tyuvta. So
that's a complete contradiction to רב הונא. Rav Huna.
So basically, which makes sense, I didn't mean
תיובתא דרב הונא, tyuvta deRav Huna, excuse me, תיובתא דרב הונא. tyuvta
deRav Huna. So it's a complete contradiction to רב הונא, Rav Huna,
it's because makes a lot of sense, right? Why should we assume
that the כהן kohen would be okay marrying a woman that's forbidden
to him if he didn't know about it? And since we presume
he's not okay, so it's a טעות, ta'ut, and she's not entitled
to a כתובה. ketubah. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says: ורב הונא
מתניתין אטעייה, veRav Huna matnisin at'yei, רב הונא Rav Huna was misled
by the
משנה. mishnah. הוא סבר, hu savar, he thought, מדקמפלג באיילונית, mideka-maflej be-aylonit,
since the משנה mishnah says if he knew that she was an
איילונית aylonit she gets a כתובה, ketubah, so it means only the
איילונית aylonit case it doesn't
matter, ולא קמפלג באלמנה, velo ka-maflej be-almanah, and it didn't say by
the אלמנה, almanah, מכלל דאלמנה אפילו בסתמא נמי אית לה, miklal de-almanah
afilu bistama nami islah, it presumed by an אלמנה almanah that you
know that even without saying anything... ולא היא, velo hi, and it's
not true. כי תני לה לאלמנה אפלוגתא דאיילונית קאי, ki tani lah
le-almanah a-pelugta de-aylonit kai, when it says by the case of the
אלמנה, almanah, right, so it's going back to the case, you know,
it's in the context of the distinction it already made by the
איילונית. aylonit. So when it said by an איילונית, aylonit, it said
איילונית aylonit doesn't get a כתובה, ketubah, but if he knows, she
does get a כתובה. ketubah. And then it said by the אלמנה,
almanah, it says אלמנה almanah does get a כתובה. ketubah. Okay, so
it says אלמנה almanah does get a כתובה, ketubah, רב הונא Rav
Huna reasonably thought it meant without making any distinction, she always gets
a כתובה. ketubah. That was a pretty reasonable read. But the גמרא
Gemara says: No, we've already framed when we talked about the איילונית
aylonit that knowing about it matters. So when we got to talking
about the אלמנה... almanah... He meant within the same type of a
context that it really matters whether you knew about it and if
you didn't know about it she doesn't. Of course, doesn't really answer
the question, because then why is אלמנה almanah in a different category
than the illness? Right? They both really have the same הלכה. halacha.
Anyway, all right.
Go ahead. Standard.
It
probably is different because of the standard.
What?
Yeah, it's standard.